♪Confessing to the moon in the rustling wind back then♪
♪จันทร์เคยแจ่มกระจ่าง♪
♪Like a boat being swallowed up among the cities♪
♪พลันแปรเป็นทะเลคลั่ง♪
♪Watching the flowers fall in unease, worries and troubles fill my mind♪
♪ตระหนกฟังเสียงบุปผาโรย♪
♪Am I going to where I want♪
♪ทุกที่ที่ไป♪
♪To stay or to leave, you decide♪
♪ด้วยการไปหรืออยู่ของเจ้า♪
♪Nations are different♪
♪ปฐพีกับแผ่นดินก็ต่างกัน♪
♪One without desire is one that is not alive♪
♪ฟ้าดินไร้ใจ♪
♪Looking at the sky side by side♪
♪ร่วมเคียงชมนภา♪
♪We've gotten closer with time♪
♪กาลเข้มข้นกว่าเวลา♪
♪One glance, the city of Chang'an is bare♪
♪มองผ่านปราดเดียว♪
♪Among the ridiculous people and things is me♪
♪ในเรื่องราวเหลวไหลของผู้คน♪
=Episode 22=
=ตอนที่ 22=
The Right Minister
โย่วเซี่ยงผู้นี้
is eccentric
ดูแปลกประหลาด
and cunning.
เหมือนมีอะไรแอบแฝง
His words are not to be trusted.
คำพูดของเขาเชื่อถือไม่ได้
But, his words did make sense.
แต่ที่เขาพูดมาต่างก็มีเหตุผลอยู่มาก
Due to the fact that he was an old friend of my grandfather,
เพราะเขาเป็นสหายเก่าแก่ของท่านปู่
that's why he was able to urge Han Yue to act.
ดังนั้นจึงบงการหานเยว่
That's why he was able to urge the descendants of the Zheng Family
บงการลูกหลานตระกูลเจิ้ง
to initiate the chain
บงการให้เรื่องราวต่อเนื่องทั้งหมดนี้
of events.
เกิดขึ้น
Because of that fact,
และด้วยเหตุนี้
he complied to Qiu Ziliang in public but opposed him in private.
จึงทำเป็นเชื่อฟังฉิวจื่อเหลียง
It's because he has an ulterior motive.
แต่ใจคิดเป็นอื่น
If, he's really our ally,
ถ้าเขาเป็นมิตรไม่ใช่ศัตรูจริง
what do you plan to do?
ท่านวางแผนจะทำอย่างไร
What do you plan to do with her?
เจ้าตั้งใจจะลงโทษอย่างไร
Learning is a never-ending process.
สองเด็กน้อยถกเรื่องตะวัน
I plan to keep her by my side.
หม่อมฉันตั้งใจว่าจะให้นางอยู่ข้างหม่อมฉัน
I'll prove her wrong with facts.
เอาเรื่องจริงมายืนยันว่านางผิด
And I hope that she can change her ways.
รอให้นางกลับใจ
That's fine.
ก็ดี
You may leave with her then.
เช่นนั้นเจ้าก็พานางไปด้วย
No.
ไม่เพคะ
I need to stay here
หม่อมฉันจะอยู่ที่นี่
in order to prevent the same thing
เพื่อป้องกันไม่ให้การลอบสังหาร
from happening again.
เกิดขึ้นอีก
No need for that.
ไม่จำเป็น
Without you,
หากไม่มีเจ้า
I wouldn't be hurt in the first place.
ข้าก็คงไม่ถูกทำร้าย
It was my negligence.
หม่อมฉันละเลยหน้าที่
I'm willing to receive punishment.
ยินดีรับโทษเพคะ
It's getting late.
ดึกมากแล้ว
I need to go to court now.
ข้าจะไปออกว่าราชการ
For today's morning court,
เช้าตรู่วันนี้
you don't need to follow me.
เจ้าไม่ต้องตามมา
I suggest you give up.
เจ้าล้มเลิกความคิดเสียเถอะ
I will never change my mind.
ข้าไม่มีทางล้มเลิกความตั้งใจหรอก
I suggest you to kill me right away.
ข้าขอเตือนเจ้า ให้จบชีวิตข้าด้วยดาบเดียวเสีย
If not, you'll face the consequences.
ไม่อย่างนั้นปัญหาก็ไม่สิ้นสุด
General Han was only able
การที่แม่ทัพหานหนีตายมาได้
to survive the Morning Dew Rebellion
จากกบฏเจาลู่ช่วงนั้นมาได้
because His Majesty had saved him.
เป็นเพราะฝ่าบาททรงช่วยเขาไว้
What?
อะไรนะ
His Majesty was the one who saved him
ฝ่าบาททรงช่วยชีวิตเขาที่มีลมหายใจ
from the mass grave when he was barely alive.
เพียงน้อยนิดออกมาจากป่าช้า
His Majesty assigned Han Ding to send General Han to Baizhang Temple.
มอบหมายให้หานติ้งพาไปส่งที่วัดไป่จ้าง
If you don't believe me,
ถ้าเจ้าไม่เชื่อ
you can confront Han Ding yourself.
ก็ไปถามหานติ้งได้
That's impossible.
จะเป็นไปได้อย่างไร
Back then, he was the one
ตอนนั้นก็เห็นชัด ๆ ว่า
who had massacred the Han Family.
เขาทำร้ายตระกูลหาน
Qiu Ziliang was extremely influential.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงมีอำนาจคับฟ้า
Back then, His Majesty
ฝ่าบาทในยามนั้น
was only
เป็นเพียงองค์ชาย
a prince with no power or influence.
ที่ไร้อำนาจบารมีพระองค์หนึ่ง
He could only follow his order.
ทำได้แต่ฟังคำสั่ง
That means he's weak.
อ่อนแอก็อ่อนแอสิ
There's no need to come up with excuses like these.
จะมาหาข้ออ้างอะไร
When we encounter such disputes,
ช่วงเวลาที่ต้องตัดสินถูกผิด
some people choose to die as a hero
บางคนเลือกตายเพื่อรักษาคุณธรรม
while some people will endure hardships and humiliations to achieve their goal.
บางคนเลือกอดทนกล้ำกลืนเพื่อศักดิ์ศรี
If, everything you said was true,
ถ้าเป็นอย่างที่เจ้าพูดจริง ๆ
if His Majesty was someone who resorted to any means
ฝ่าบาทก็คงเป็นคนที่ทำอะไรไม่เลือกวิธี
to get his hands on the throne,
เพื่อให้ได้บัลลังก์มา
why would the current Qiu Ziliang
ถ้าเช่นนั้นฉิวจื่อเหลียงในตอนนี้
detest and reject him?
ทำไมต้องทอดทิ้งพระองค์
Why would he force him to step down from the throne then?
บังคับให้พระองค์สละบัลลังก์ด้วยเล่า
He...
เขา
He just thinks that he's capable enough to escape from his grasp.
เพราะเขาอยากปีกกล้าขาแข็งอย่างไรเล่า
Anyway,
สรุปแล้ว
I will never forgive Qi Yan.
ข้าไม่มีทางอภัยให้ฉีเยี่ยนแน่นอน
I know.
ข้ารู้
It's impossible for me to eliminate your hatred for him
ว่าในใจเจ้ามีความแค้นฝังลึก
with just my words.
ไม่สามารถใช้คำพูดมาโน้มน้าวได้
After all,
แต่โดยแก่นแท้
you're just picking on someone who's weaker than you.
เจ้าก็แค่รังแกผู้ด้อย กลัวผู้แกร่งเท่านั้นสินะ
What did you say?
อะไรนะ
His Majesty is weak and not influential.
ฝ่าบาททรงมีกำลังไม่มากพอ
He's much easier to kill compared with Qiu Ziliang.
สังหารได้ง่ายกว่าฉิวจื่อเหลียง
And, you were planning to die.
แต่เจ้ากลับเรียกร้องความตาย
You're just using His Majesty as your scapegoat.
ดังนั้นก็เลยอยากให้ฝ่าบาทมารับผิดร่วมกัน
You think that your dead family members
เจ้าคิดว่าถ้าปลงพระชนม์ฝ่าบาทไป
will be appeased
ก็จะทำให้ครอบครัวที่อยู่บนสวรรค์
once you killed His Majesty.
สบายใจกว่าเดิมสินะ
Nonsense.
พูดจาไร้สาระ
Enough.
เอาละ
Since it has come to this,
เรื่องก็มาถึงจุดนี้แล้ว
I don't wish
ข้าเองก็ไม่อยากเถียง
to argue with you anymore.
เรื่องถูกผิดอะไรกับเจ้าแล้ว
When I was treating your wound,
ตอนที่ข้าเพิ่งจะทำแผลให้เจ้า
I realised
ข้าเห็นว่า
that you were injured
ก่อนที่เจ้าจะลอบสังหาร
before you attempted to assassinate His Majesty.
บนตัวก็มีบาดแผลอยู่แล้ว
What exactly is going on?
เกิดอะไรขึ้นกันแน่
When the nest is overturned, no egg stays unbroken.
ใต้รังที่แตกยังมีไข่ที่สมบูรณ์
That beast, Wang Lin,
หวังหลินสารเลวนั่น
he sent his men to surround Almond Forest.
ล้อมป่าซิ่งจื่อเอาไว้
I...
ข้า
Sir,
ใต้เท้า
we've slain 32 soldiers of the Zhenwu Army
พวกเราสังหารคนของทัพเจิ้นอู๋
inside Almond Forest.
ในป่าซิ่งจื่อได้ 32 คน
Besides that, we managed to capture her as well.
แล้วยังจับสตรีนางนี้มาได้
She's the servant of Han Yue.
นางเป็นบ่าวรับใช้ของหานเยว่
Her name is Ziyuan.
นามว่าจื่อย่วน
You guys may leave.
ออกไปได้
Yes, sir.
ขอรับ
When that darned eunuch wasn't paying attention,
ข้าฉวยโอกาสตอนที่ขันทีชั่วนั่นเผลอ
I stole his keys and escaped from him.
ขโมยกุญแจแล้วหนีออกมา
Just wait and see.
เจ้าคอยดูเถอะ
For the humiliations that I've suffered,
ความอับอายที่ข้าได้รับ
I will pay them back to you guys
จะคืนพวกเจ้าสิบเท่า ยี่สิบเท่า
tenfold.
อย่างแน่นอน
Wang Lin was the one who had humiliated you.
คนที่หยามเกียรติเจ้าคือหวังหลิน
But, you're actually
เจ้าก็จะเอาความแค้นนี้
blaming His Majesty for this?
ไปลงที่ฝ่าบาทด้วยอย่างนั้นหรือ
You're Qi Yan's lackey indeed.
ฉีเยี่ยนสุนัขรับใช้ของเจ้านี่แหละ
I told you before.
ข้าเคยบอกแล้ว
I will prove you wrong.
ว่าข้าจะพิสูจน์ว่า เจ้าน่ะคิดผิด
Uncle,
เรื่องที่ข้า
regarding the favour I've asked of you,
ขอร้องเสด็จอาก่อนหน้านี้
please complete it as soon as possible.
ขอให้เสด็จอาเร่งมือด้วย
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาทเป็นคนตรัส
were you referring to Yu'er?
แต่ว่าอวี๋เอ๋อร์
Yes.
ใช่
After Aunt Ninghe's death,
พอท่านอาหนิงเหอตายไป
I'm afraid the situation in Lucong will change.
เกรงว่าแผนการหลูฉงจะเปลี่ยนไป
Please bring her away.
พานางไปด้วย
If all of us are leaving,
พวกเราไปหมดแล้ว
what about you?
แล้วพระองค์ล่ะ
This concerns my survival in the first place.
เดิมทีนี่ก็เป็นช่วงชี้เป็นชี้ตายของข้า
I
ข้า
will stay here until the very last moment.
จะต้องปกป้องจนถึงนาทีสุดท้าย
Lady Li.
คุณหนูหลี่
Are you heading to your post?
ไปเข้าเวรหรือ
Yes.
เจ้าค่ะ
My father
วันนี้พ่อข้า
went to find His Majesty today.
ไปคุยธุระกับฝ่าบาท
Do you know what they talked about?
เจ้ารู้หรือไม่ว่าพวกเขาคุยอะไรกันบ้าง
Lady Li, please get straight to the point.
คุณหนูหลี่มีอะไรก็เชิญพูดมาตามตรง
So, His Majesty's women
สตรีของฝ่าบาทสองนาง
are actually facing off against each other.
กำลังปะทะกันอยู่
Go and investigate
ไปสืบมาหน่อย
what exactly happened
ว่าระหว่างพวกนาง
between them.
มีอะไรเกิดขึ้น
All right.
ได้เลย
They plan to send someone to Lucong
พวกเขาอยากหาคนไปที่หลูฉง
in order to meet up with the person left by Ninghe
ไปติดต่อกับคนที่หนิงเหอ
and exchange information
หลงเหลือไว้อีกครั้ง
so that they can acquire intel regarding Lucong's current military situation.
ควบคุมการทหารของหลูฉง
To find a suitable candidate,
คนผู้นั้น
firstly,
ข้อแรก
the person must be dependable.
ต้องเชื่อถือได้
Secondly,
ข้อสอง
the person must be skilled in martial arts
ต้องมีวรยุทธสูงส่ง
so that he or she may avoid Qiu Ziliang's assassination attempt.
หลบหนีการไล่ล่าของฉิวจื่อเหลียงได้
Thirdly,
ข้อสาม
the person must be fearless of death.
ต้องไม่กลัวตาย
You understand what I mean, right?
เจ้าเข้าใจความหมายข้าหรือไม่
I'm sure you know who the person is.
ว่าคนผู้นี้คือใคร
Lady Li, thank you for pointing it out.
ขอบคุณคุณหนูหลี่ที่ชี้แนะ
My lady,
คุณหนู
is she Cheng Ruoyu?
นี่น่ะหรือเฉิงรั่วอวี๋
I heard that Grand Empress Dowager
ได้ยินว่าเมื่อวานนี้ไท่หวงไท่โฮ่ว
gave her the Peach Blossom Jade Bangle yesterday.
ทรงมอบกำไลเถาเยาให้นางด้วยเจ้าค่ะ
The peach trees are in full blossom.
ไล่ไปให้ไกล
Look at her.
เจ้าดูนางสิ
Do you think she deserves such fortune?
เหมือนกับคนที่มีบุญวาสนาหรือไม่เล่า
Of course not.
ไม่มีอยู่แล้วเจ้าค่ะ
Only our lady
มีเพียงคุณหนูของเราเท่านั้น
is worthy enough to be His Majesty's woman.
ที่เหมาะสมคู่ควรกับฝ่าบาท
Is that person the goddaughter of Duke Chu?
คนผู้นั้นคือบุตรีบุญธรรมของฉู่กั๋วกงหรือ
Yes, my lady.
เจ้าค่ะ
His Majesty, Chen Yintai
เฉินอิ้นไถ
couldn't wait for you to assign his post to him any longer.
รอรับขวานอาญาสิทธิ์ จากพระองค์ไม่ไหว
Now,
บัดนี้
he's trying to win the hearts of every faction.
พยายามทำให้ทุกพื้นที่ย่ำแย่ลง
The power that Shi Quanzhong
สื่อเฉวียนจง
had left for Princess Ninghe
กำลังคนที่หลงเหลือให้ท่านหญิงหนิงเหอ
has lost its pillar of stability.
บัดนี้ก็สูญเสียความเชื่อมั่นไปแล้ว
Some had already joined
ในจำนวนนี้ก็มีคน
Chen Yintai's faction.
ที่ไปเข้าพวกกับเฉินอิ้นไถแล้ว
Since we can use these people to our advantage,
ในเมื่อพวกเราหลอกใช้คนพวกนี้ได้
I'm sure Qiu Ziliang can do the same.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงก็ทำได้เช่นกัน
I'm sure
พวกเขาจะต้อง
they've come up with a plan.
ไปปรึกษาอะไรกันมาก่อนแล้วแน่นอน
That's why
เพราะฉะนั้น
they killed Princess Ninghe to vent out their frustration.
ถึงได้สังหารท่านหญิงหนิงเหอ เพื่อระบายความแค้น
The killer
คนลงมือฆ่า
is ruthless and cunning indeed.
โหดเหี้ยมจริง ๆ
Back then, when I sent Princess Lucong
ตอนที่กระหม่อมไปหลูฉง
to Lucong for her marriage,
เพื่อส่งตัวท่านหญิงหนิงเหอ เข้าเรือนหอคราวนั้น
I once saw Chen Yintai before.
เคยพบเฉินอิ้นไถผู้นี้มาก่อน
Although he's ugly,
แม้หน้าตาเกลี้ยงเกลา
I heard that he's a decisive man.
แต่ได้ยินว่าทำงานเด็ดเดี่ยว
He's good at training soldiers as well.
มีกลวิธีในการฝึกทหาร
Even if the princess were still alive,
ต่อให้ท่านหญิงยังมีชีวิตอยู่
our men in Lucong
คนที่อยู่ที่หลูฉง
might still not be able to control the situation.
ก็ยังไม่สามารถควบคุมสถานการณ์ได้
So, this time,
เพราะฉะนั้นคนที่พวกเรา
we need to choose
จะให้ไปหาหลูฉงในครั้งนี้
the best candidate we have before sending them to Lucong.
จำเป็นต้องเลือกเป็นอย่างดี
Besides
นอกจากจะติดต่อ
contacting the Zhi Quanzhong's loyal retainers,
กลุ่มของสื่อเฉวียนจงได้แล้ว
the most important thing is for us
สำคัญที่สุด
to understand the situation in Lucong
ต้องเข้าใจสถานการณ์ที่หลูฉงเป็นอย่างดี
and control the situation
ควบคุมสถานการณ์ให้ได้
so that Chen Yintai doesn't dare to act rashly.
ไม่ให้เฉินอิ้นไถกล้าทำอะไรบุ่มบ่าม
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
I'm willing to be your candidate.
หม่อมฉันขอเดินทางไป
Your Majesty, I hope I can share your burden.
หม่อมฉันหวังช่วยแบ่งเบาภาระแทนพระองค์
Please send me to Lucong.
ไปหลูฉงเพคะ
I've selected another candidate for this matter.
เรื่องนี้ให้คนอื่นไปทำแล้ว
Your Majesty, whom do you plan to send?
ฝ่าบาทตั้งพระทัยว่า จะมอบหมายให้ใครไปหรือเพคะ
You don't need to know.
เรื่องนี้เจ้าไม่ต้องรู้หรอก
Official Li,
ใต้เท้าหลี่
have you selected a suitable candidate?
ท่านมีตัวเลือกแล้วหรือ
This...
เรื่องนี้
If you don't have a suitable candidate,
ถ้าท่านไม่มีคนละก็
what do you think about me?
ท่านคิดว่าข้าพอได้หรือไม่
Leave.
ออกไป
Official Li,
ใต้เท้าหลี่
I hope you can persuade His Majesty
หวังว่าท่านจะโน้มน้าวฝ่าบาทได้
to send me there.
ให้ข้าไปเถอะ
I will never allow it.
ข้าไม่อนุญาต
The candidate we will send to Lucong
คนที่จะไปหลูฉง
will be decided by His Majesty.
ฝ่าบาทจะเป็นคนตัดสิน
Your Majesty, I will resume with my work.
กระหม่อมขอตัวไปจัดการธุระก่อน
Get up.
ลุกขึ้น
I have another arrangement for you.
ข้ามีงานอื่นจะให้เจ้าทำ
Uncle will be heading back to his hermitage.
เสด็จอาจะกลับไปปลีกวิเวก
I'm worried for his safety.
ข้าเป็นห่วงความปลอดภัยของพวกเขา
You can let Madam Jade accompany him.
ให้อวี้เหนียงไปกับเขาสิเพคะ
Uncle said he wanted you to accompany him.
เสด็จอาบอกว่าต้องการเจ้า
The situation in Lucong is undetermined.
ตอนนี้สถานการณ์ของหลูฉงยังไม่แน่นอน
It's very dangerous.
ค่อนข้างอันตราย
And, Qiu Ziliang
ทั้งยังมีฉิวจื่อเหลียง
is waiting for a chance to attack us.
คอยจับจ้องอยู่ไม่ห่าง
I'm not afraid.
หม่อมฉันไม่กลัว
I know what to do.
หม่อมฉันมีวิธีเพคะ
Yu'er,
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
I know what to do as well.
ข้าก็มีวิธีเหมือนกัน
Let me help you.
ให้หม่อมฉันช่วยพระองค์
You're really loyal
ฮ่องเต้สุนัขรับใช้ของเจ้า
to that darned emperor.
ช่างจงรักภักดีจริง ๆ นะ
You want to head to Lucong personally?
ยังจะไปหลูฉงด้วยตัวเองอีก
You will follow me.
เจ้าไปด้วยกันกับข้า
What did you say?
เจ้าว่าอะไรนะ
I told you to follow me to Lucong.
ข้าบอกว่าให้เจ้าไปกับข้า
Why are you here?
ท่านมาทำอะไร
I heard that Grand Empress Dowager
ได้ยินว่าไท่หวงไท่โฮ่ว
has rewarded you with the Peach Blossom Jade Bangle.
ประทานกำไลเถาเยาให้แก่เจ้า
I'm here to take a look.
ก็เลยตั้งใจมาดูสักหน่อย
I've returned it to Grand Empress Dowager.
ข้าคืนไปแล้ว
You became smarter.
ครั้งนี้ฉลาดขึ้นแล้วสินะ
You're right.
ก็ใช่
It's better for you to return it sooner
ของที่ไม่คู่ควร
when it doesn't suit you.
คืนแต่เนิ่น ๆ ก็ดีแล้ว
It doesn't suit me?
ถ้าข้าไม่คู่ควร
Do you think it suits you then?
แล้วท่านคู่ควรอย่างนั้นหรือ
You mustn't forget this.
ท่านอย่าได้ลืมเชียวล่ะ
His Majesty has rejected you
ฝ่าบาททรงปฏิเสธท่าน
time and time again.
ครั้งแล้วครั้งเล่า
What?
ทำไมล่ะ
Are you jealous?
หึงอย่างนั้นหรือ
Wretched servant.
พวกบ่าวไพร่
You're still keeping her alive?
ยังเก็บตัววิบัติไว้อีกหรือ
Useless wretch who had betrayed your master,
คนชั่วช้าหักหลังนายท่านอย่างเจ้า
I'll kill you with my own hands!
ข้าจะฆ่าซะ
I think you should kill her.
ฆ่าเสียเถอะ
She has deep hatred for us.
นางเกลียดพวกเราขนาดนี้
She's a recipe for disaster.
สุดท้ายก็จะเป็นปัญหาไม่จบไม่สิ้น
I'm different from you.
ข้าไม่เหมือนท่านหรอกนะ
I don't kill people.
ข้าไม่ฆ่าคน
You don't kill people?
ไม่ฆ่าคน
Tell me.
ว่ามาเถอะ
Why are you here
ที่ท่านมาวันนี้
today?
มีเรื่องอะไรกันแน่
I heard that you're heading to Lucong.
ได้ยินว่าเจ้าจะไปหลูฉง
There are plenty of spies within the palace.
ในวังมีคนคอยสอดแนมขนาดนี้
Do you think
เจ้าคิดว่า
you can keep this a secret
เจ้าจะปิดฟ้าข้ามทะเล
and head to Lucong without facing any trouble?
ไปถึงหลูฉงอย่างปลอดภัยได้อย่างนั้นหรือ
That's why
ดังนั้น
I've come up
ข้าจึงคิดหาวิธี
with a solution.
จัดการปัญหานี้ได้แล้ว
Seems like
ดูท่า
we're thinking of the same thing.
พวกเราก็คงคิดตรงกัน
Stop the carriage.
หยุดรถก่อน
Newcomer,
เจ้าหน้าใหม่
don't you even recognise the Chess Bearer?
แม้แต่ผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกก็ไม่รู้จักอย่างนั้นหรือ
Chess Bearer, you're welcome to exit the palace.
น้อมส่งผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกออกจากวัง
How do you plan to investigate Chen Yintai
หลังจากถึงหลูฉงแล้ว
once
เจ้าวางแผนว่า
you've reached Lucong?
จะไปสืบหาเบื้องหลังของเฉินอิ้นไถอย่างไร
I'll act accordingly.
สบโอกาสลงมือ
What if they have a tight security
หากในกองทัพป้องกันแน่นหนา
and you have no chance to do so?
สบโอกาสไม่ได้เล่า
That won't be the case.
จะเป็นไปได้อย่างไร
Chen Yintai
เฉินอิ้นไถ
always wanted His Majesty to assign him the post.
อยากได้ขวานอาญาสิทธิ์ของฝ่าบาทมาตลอด
I'm sure he doesn't dare to neglect me
ในเมื่อข้าเป็นคนที่ถูกส่งมาจากเหิงอัน
when I come from Heng'an City.
เขาไม่กล้าเพิกเฉยแน่นอน
Why don't you give me some tips?
ไม่อย่างนั้นท่านก็คิดอุบายให้ข้าหน่อยสิ
Why should I do so?
เพราะอะไรล่ะ
You should do so
ถือซะว่า
in order to help out your future husband.
ช่วยเหลือสามีของท่านในอนาคตอย่างไรล่ะ
We're safe now.
ปลอดภัยแล้ว
You can get off the carriage
พาสุนัขบ้าของเจ้าตัวนั้น
with your crazy lackey.
ลงรถไปเถอะ
Don't do this.
อย่าสิ ๆ
Why don't you send me out of the city?
ไม่อย่างนั้นท่านก็ส่งข้าออกเมืองเถอะ
By the way,
จริงสิ
you should prepare a great horse for me.
เอาม้าดี ๆ ให้ข้าหนึ่งตัวด้วย
That way,
แบบนี้
the people of the Chess of Generals Camp
คนของสำนักหมากรุก
won't chase after me.
ก็ไม่ตามข้ามาแล้ว
Why don't you
เจ้าก็บอกให้
tell me
ข้าไปส่งเจ้า
to send you to Lucong directly?
ที่หลูฉงเลยสิ
That won't do.
แบบนั้นไม่ได้หรอก
If you send me out,
ถ้าท่านออกไปส่งข้าละก็
Qiu Ziliang will chase after me.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงต้องตามข้ามาแน่นอน
I won't be able to go out by then.
แบบนั้นข้าจะออกไปได้อย่างไร
Farewell.
ขอลา
You're helping her to get to Lucong.
ท่านช่วยให้นางไปหลูฉง
If Eunuch Qiu finds out...
ถ้ากงกงรู้เรื่องขึ้นมา
I'm the hostage right now.
ข้าถูกบังคับอย่างไรล่ะ
I didn't expect...
ไม่คิดเลย
You didn't expect what?
ไม่คิดเลยว่าอะไร
I didn't expect you
ไม่คิดว่านี่ขนาดยัง
to buy the people's hearts
ไม่ทันได้เป็นฮองเฮา
before you become the empress.
ก็รู้จักซื้อใจคนแล้ว
You mean I tried to bribe Cheng Ruoyu?
ซื้อตัวเฉิงรั่วอวี๋
You covered up for her and you even gave her a horse.
ทั้งคอยคุ้มกัน ทั้งส่งม้าให้
Isn't it obvious that you're trying to buy her heart?
ถ้าไม่เรียกว่าซื้อใจแล้วจะเรียกว่าอะไร
What?
ทำไมล่ะ
Are you trying to establish
เริ่มบ่มเพาะอำนาจ
your influence within the harem right now?
ในวังหลังแล้วอย่างนั้นหรือ
That's why
เพราะฉะนั้น
you must cover up for me.
เจ้าก็ต้องช่วยข้ากลบเกลื่อนด้วย
Father,
ท่านพ่อ
Cheng Ruoyu used me as a hostage
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋ฉวยโอกาสตอนที่ข้าไม่ระวัง
and left the palace when I wasn't paying attention.
ลักพาตัวข้าออกจากวัง
She even stole my horse.
แล้วยังเอาม้าของข้าไป
If it weren't for the Left Advisor,
ถ้าไม่ใช่ว่าจั่วซื่อตามไปได้ทัน
I would've been...
ลูกกลัว
Ruoyu is bullying me because I don't know any martial arts.
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋รังแกข้าที่ไม่เป็นวรยุทธ
She has humiliated me.
ลบหลู่ข้าถึงเพียงนี้
Please lend me 100 soldiers from your Shencai Army.
ข้าขอยืมทหารกล้าทัพเสินไฉร้อยนาย
I must pursue her.
ข้าจะไปฆ่านาง
You should rest up for now.
เจ้ารักษาแผลก่อนจะดีกว่า
Regarding that matter,
เรื่องนี้
I will send someone else
ข้าจะมอบหมายให้คนอื่น
to do the job.
ไปจัดการ
Yes, Father.
เจ้าค่ะ
When I was barely conscious,
ตอนที่ข้าหมดสติ
I think I heard Cheng Ruoyu saying
เหมือนว่าจะได้ยินเฉิงรั่วอวี๋
to Ziyuan
พูดกับจื่อย่วน
that she was heading to Zhaoyi.
ว่าจะไปจ้าวอี๋
Isn't she heading to Lucong?
ไม่ได้จะไปหลูฉงหรอกหรือ
What can she do by herself
นางไปที่หลูฉงลำพังคนเดียว
even if she was heading to Lucong?
จะจัดการอะไรได้
She's heading to Zhaoyi.
นางต้องการไปจ้าวอี๋
She's going to see the nephew of Liu Congjian,
นางต้องการพบหลานชายหลิวฉงเจียน
Liu Zhi.
หลิวจื้อ
She's right.
ขอรับ
After our men had arrived at Zhaoyi,
หลังจากที่คนของพวกเราไปถึงจ้าวอี๋
we found out that Liu Congjian was dead
ตามสืบมาหลายครั้งถึงได้รู้ว่า
after our investigation.
หลิวฉงเจียนตายแล้ว
And his nephew, Liu Zhi,
แต่หลานชายเขา หลิวจื้อ
didn't announce the news in public.
ปิดบังไม่รายงาน
He only sent His Majesty a secret letter,
แต่แอบส่งรายงานลับต่อฝ่าบาท
requesting for the post of military commissioner.
ขอสืบตำแหน่งผู้บัญชาการมณฑลทหารต่อ
I've ordered Gao Ping
รายงานลับ
to steal the secret letter.
ข้าน้อยสั่งให้เกาผิงไปขโมยมา
So, how many local officials
ตามหน่วยงานยังมีอีกกี่แห่ง
are doing the same thing?
ที่มีรายงานลับแบบนี้
Father, please don't be angry.
ท่านพ่อโปรดระงับโทสะ
Since
ในเมื่อ
Liu Zhi doesn't appreciate
หลิวจื้อไม่รู้จักบุญคุณคน
our kindness, just like his uncle,
เหมือนอาของเขา
we should kill him.
ก็ฆ่าเลยดีกว่า
Right Advisor.
โย่วซื่อ
Yes, my lord.
เจ้าค่ะ
Did you hear that?
ได้ยินหรือยัง
Settle this quickly.
รีบไปจัดการเรื่องนี้ซะ
By the way,
จริงสิ
capture Cheng Ruoyu
ไปเอาตัวเฉิงรั่วอวี๋
for me as well.
กลับมาให้ข้าด้วย
Yes, my lord.
เจ้าค่ะ
Left Advisor,
จั่วซื่อ
do you know your mistake?
รู้ความผิดใช่หรือไม่
Yes, my lord.
ขอรับ
You knew that the Chess Bearer doesn't know any martial arts.
รู้อยู่แล้วว่าผู้นำสำนักหมากรุกไม่เป็นวรยุทธ
You should've stayed beside her at all times.
ก็ยังไม่คุ้มครองนางให้ดี
Go out and receive your 10 lashes.
ออกไป รับแส้สิบครั้ง
Yes, my lord.
ขอรับ
Throughout our journey,
ตลอดทางที่ผ่านมา
we saw ruined cities
เมืองแตกพินาศ
and how the people are suffering.
ชาวบ้านทุกข์เข็ญ
The prefectures are in chaos,
หัวเมืองไม่สงบ
and the foreign tribes are waiting for their chance to invade our nation.
ชนต่างเผ่าก็จ้องตาเป็นมัน
So,
เจ้าคิดว่า
who should be blamed for this?
นี่เป็นความผิดของใคร
Didn't all of this happen
ที่เป็นเช่นนี้
because of that useless emperor?
ไม่ใช่เพราะฮ่องเต้สุนัขนั่นไร้สามารถหรือ
For the past 40 years, the Xing empire
สี่สิบปีมานี้ต้าซิง
had 6 emperors.
เปลี่ยนฮ่องเต้ไปหกพระองค์
Even the emperor's throne isn't stable.
ขนาดฮ่องเต้ยังไร้เสถียรภาพ
How could the people live in peace?
แล้วประชาชนจะอยู่อย่างเป็นสุขได้อย่างไร
Only a long rule
การปกครองที่ยั่งยืน
can establish a peaceful society.
สันติสุขจึงยาวนาน
His Majesty has such a majestic ambition.
ฝ่าบาททรงมีปณิธานที่ยิ่งใหญ่เช่นนี้
But,
แล้วทำไม
why can't we
จึงไม่ให้โอกาสพระองค์
give him a chance to atone for his mistake?
ได้ทำคุณไถ่โทษสักครั้งเล่า
Ziyuan,
จื่อย่วน
you and I are clear
เจ้ากับข้าต่างรู้ดี
that the eunuch's faction is responsible for the chaos.
ขันทีคือต้นเหตุแห่งเภทภัยของต้าซิง
Only by getting rid of them
มีเพียงกำจัดพวกขันทีให้สิ้นซาก
will we be able to prevent a tragedy like the Morning Dew Rebellion
โศกนาฏกรรมดังเช่นเจาลู่
from happening again.
จึงจะไม่เกิดขึ้นอีก
General Han didn't understand that fact.
แม่ทัพหานมองประเด็นนี้ไม่ทะลุ
I hope you can reconsider your view
ข้าหวังว่าเจ้าจะใคร่ครวญให้ดี
and understand the situation.
มองให้เข้าใจ
You must be the one the imperial court had sent here
เจ้าคือคนที่ราชสำนักส่งมา
to assign me the post.
มอบขวานอาญาสิทธิ์สินะ
That's right.
ถูกต้อง
I'm here under His Majesty's order.
ข้ารับพระบัญชาจากฝ่าบาทมา
You've murdered the military commissioner, Shi Quanzong.
ท่านฆ่าผู้บัญชาการมณฑลทหารสื่อเฉวียนจง
Now, the army of Lucong is in chaos.
บัดนี้เกิดจลาจลในทัพหลูฉง
The foreign tribes are waiting for their chance to invade our nation.
ชนต่างเผ่าจ้องตาเป็นมัน
The people are suffering.
ชาวบ้านทุกข์ทนข้นแค้น
Today,
วันนี้
I'm here to get an explanation from you.
ข้ามาเพื่อขอคำอธิบายจากท่าน
You want an explanation?
คำอธิบาย
Ninghe is dead.
หนิงเหอตายไปแล้ว
I've slain
คนสนิทของสื่อเฉวียนจง
Zhi Quanzhong's trusted followers as well.
ก็ถูกข้าฆ่าไปจนเกลี้ยง
Now, Lucong
ตอนนี้หลูฉง
is under my control completely.
อยู่ในความควบคุมของข้าอย่างเด็ดขาด
Instead of waiting for the imperial court to give me a position,
แทนที่จะอยู่ใต้อาณัติของราชสำนัก
I would rather establish my own nation.
ข้าสู้ตั้งตัวเป็นฮ่องเต้เสียเอง
What do you think?
ไม่ดีกว่าหรือ
Yu'er!
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Han Ding,
หานติ้ง
where is Yu'er currently at?
อวี๋เอ๋อร์ไปถึงไหนแล้ว
We received news from her six hours ago.
สามชั่วยามก่อนเพิ่งได้รับข่าวว่า
She has reached the border of Lucong.
เข้าเขตชายแดนหลูฉงแล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
So,
เช่นนั้นตอนนี้
have she met Chen Yintai?
น่าจะได้เจอกับเฉินอิ้นไถแล้วกระมัง
Your Majesty, don't worry.
ฝ่าบาททรงวางพระทัยได้
Our men are protecting her
ที่นั่นมีคนของพวกเรา
in secret.
คอยลอบคุ้มกัน
What's the news?
ว่าอย่างไร
Cheng Ruoyu has arrived at Lucong.
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋ไปถึงหลูฉงแล้ว
What about Qiu Ziliang?
ทางด้านฉิวจื่อเหลียงล่ะ
Liu Zhi has a large number of soldiers on his hand.
หลิวจื้อกุมทหารในมือ
The Shencai Army general who Eunuch Qiu had sent
ใต้เท้าส่งแม่ทัพแห่งทัพเสินไฉไป
was slain by him immediately.
ก็ถูกเขาฆ่าทิ้งโดยไม่ถามไถ่
The soldiers who were sent there in secret
ทหารเบี้ยที่ลอบส่งไป
were slain when they entered the Liu Residence.
พอเข้าจวนหลิวก็ถูกเก็บจนเรียบ
Great.
ดีมาก
I'm sure Qiu Ziliang will be enraged.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงต้องโกรธมากแน่
The more he's enraged with Liu Zhi's action,
เขายิ่งทุ่มโทสะใส่หลิวจื้อ
the less attention he'll be able to pay
ก็ยิ่งไม่อาจแบ่งสมาธิ
to the other areas.
ไปดูแลที่อื่นได้
So,
ดังนั้น
this trick of yours
เป้าที่ท่านหามาชิ้นนี้
is effective indeed.
นับว่ามีประโยชน์จริง ๆ
Over here.
มา ไปทางนี้
Stop right there.
หยุดก่อน
Who are you guys?
พวกเจ้าเป็นใคร
I'm the Sword Bearer of the Violet Bureau,
ผู้ถือกระบี่หน่วยอาภรณ์ม่วง
Upper Rank Five female official, Cheng Ruoyu.
นางข้าหลวงระดับที่ห้า เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
She's my attendant, Ziyuan.
ผู้ติดตามจื่อย่วน
We're here under His Majesty's order.
รับพระบัญชาจากฝ่าบาทให้มา
Please wait a moment.
ทั้งสองท่านโปรดรอสักครู่
Please remove your weapon.
ได้โปรดปลดอาวุธด้วย
What?
ทำไม
Look at the amount of people you have.
พวกเจ้ามีตั้งมากมาย
Don't tell me you're afraid of two girls?
ยังกลัวผู้หญิงอย่างเราสองคน
Since ancient times,
นับแต่โบราณ
only the emperor's subordinates need to remove their weapon
มีแต่ตอนที่ขุนนางเข้าพบเจ้าชีวิตเท่านั้น
when they see the emperor.
จึงต้องถอดเกราะปลดกระบี่
Both of us are here under His Majesty's order.
เราสองคนรับราชโองการมา
We haven't even blamed you guys
ยังไม่ทันเอาเรื่อง
for not greeting us although we're here under His Majesty's order.
ที่พวกเจ้าไม่ตั้งขบวนต้อนรับเลย
Since you're here under His Majesty's order,
ในเมื่อเป็นผู้แทนพระองค์
Naturally, I,
(ผู้บังคับกองพันหลูฉง เฉินอิ้นไถ) กระหม่อม
Chen Yintai,
เฉินอิ้นไถ
must greet you, my lady.
สมควรต้อนรับด้วยตัวเอง
But,
ทว่า
When a general is outside from the palace,
แม่ทัพอยู่ภายนอก
they may choose not to embrace a military order.
มีสิทธิ์ไม่รับราชโองการ
When you enter my tent,
ค่ายหลูฉงของข้า
you need to follow my rules.
มีกฎระเบียบภายใน
Both of you,
รบกวนทั้งสองท่าน
please suit the convenience of the host.
ปฏิบัติตามด้วย
Please.
เชิญ
- Come, let's drink. - Please.
มา ๆ ๆ เชิญดื่ม เชิญ ๆ ๆ
- Bottoms up.
- หมดจอก
My ladies, please.
ใต้เท้าผู้แทนพระองค์ทั้งสอง เชิญด้านใน
My lady,
ใต้เท้าผู้แทนพระองค์
regarding the day I receive my post,
ราชสำนักได้กำหนดวัน
have the imperial court set a date for it?
ทำพิธีมอบขวานอาญาสิทธิ์หรือยัง
Our general
ทหารคนสนิทอย่างพวกเรา
might not be able to wait any longer.
ใกล้จะรอไม่ไหวแล้วนะ
I'm unclear regarding the date
ฝ่าบาทจะพระราชทานเมื่อใด
His Majesty will assign you the post.
ข้าก็ไม่ทราบชัด
But, both of us are here
แต่จุดประสงค์ที่เราสองคนมาครั้งนี้
to investigate
เพื่อตรวจสอบ
the death of Shi Quanzhong, the late military commissioner.
การตายของผู้บัญชาการมณฑลทหารสื่อเฉวียนจง
What did you say?
เจ้าว่าอย่างไรนะ
My lady,
ใต้เท้าผู้แทนพระองค์
the man is dead.
คนผู้นั้นตายไปแล้ว
We should just forget about it.
เรื่องก็เป็นอันสิ้นสุด
I don't know
ข้าไม่รู้ว่าพวกท่านทั้งสอง
what else you two want to investigate.
คิดจะตรวจสอบอะไรอีก
Shi Quanzhong
สื่อเฉวียนจง
was assigned the post of military commissioner
เป็นทหารคนสนิทที่อดีตฮ่องเต้ทรงแต่งตั้ง
by the late emperor.
ทั้งได้รับขวานอาญาสิทธิ์
He died all of a sudden.
จู่ ๆ ก็มาตาย
We at least need to give the soldiers
ก็ควรจะมีคำอธิบายต่อบรรดาแม่ทัพ
a proper explanation regarding his death.
ทุกท่านมิใช่หรือ
My ladies,
ข้าว่าผู้แทนพระองค์ทั้งสอง
I'm sure you two are exhausted.
คงจะเดินทางมาเหน็ดเหนื่อย
Someone.
ทหาร
Yes, sir.
ขอรับ
Bring them to their tent.
พาทั้งสองท่านไปพักผ่อน
My ladies, please.
เชิญทั้งสองท่าน
This is your tent.
เป็นที่นี่ขอรับ
My ladies, please rest early.
ผู้แทนพระองค์ทั้งสองรีบพักผ่อน
Why did you say
ทำไมเจ้าถึงพูดว่า
that we're here
พวกเรามาตรวจสอบเรื่อง
to investigate Shi Quanzhong's death?
การตายของสื่อเฉวียนจง
Aren't you afraid that...
เจ้าไม่กลัวว่า
Lucong is a huge place.
หลูฉงกว้างใหญ่
There are over 1,000 men
ในค่ายทหารแห่งนี้
inside the military camp.
บนล่างมีคนเกือบพัน
How are we going
พวกเราจะติดต่อ
to contact the person whom Princess Ninghe
กับคนของท่านหญิงหนิงเหอ
had left behind?
ได้อย่างไร
Don't tell me you want us to ask them one by one?
หรือจะให้ไปถามทีละคน
If so, why don't we
มิสู้
just tell them
พวกเราชิงประกาศ
about our identities and stand first?
สถานะและจุดยืนของตัวเองออกไป
That way, the person we need to contact
เช่นนี้คนที่มีใจช่วย
will find us naturally.
ก็จะเดินมาหาเอง
Aren't you afraid
แล้วเจ้าไม่กลัวว่า
that Chen Yintai will kill us?
เฉินอิ้นไถจะฆ่าพวกเราหรือ
What? Are you afraid?
เจ้ากลัวเหรอ
Of course I'm not.
จ้างข้าก็ไม่กลัว
Don't worry.
ไม่ต้องห่วง
Chen Yintai doesn't dare to kill me,
เฉินอิ้นไถไม่กล้าฆ่าข้า
just like how I don't dare to kill him.
เหมือนกับที่ข้าไม่กล้าฆ่าเฉินอิ้นไถ
Rest early.
รีบพักผ่อนเถอะ
Maybe we'll receive news by tonight.
บางทีคืนนี้อาจจะมีข่าวก็ได้
My lady, please show mercy.
แม่นางไว้ชีวิต
I'm not here to harm you.
บริวารไม่ได้มีจุดประสงค์ร้าย
You better tell me who you are.
ยังไม่รีบประกาศสังกัดตัวเอง
If not, I'll summon the guards.
ไม่เช่นนั้นข้าจะเรียกทหารยามนะ
Don't shout.
อย่าเรียก
It won't be beneficial to both of us
หากคนของเฉินอิ้นไถมา
if Chen Yintai's men were to come.
ล้วนไม่เป็นผลดีต่อเราทั้งสองฝ่าย
Who wrote this letter?
ใครเป็นคนเขียนจดหมายนี้
Are you a subordinate of Princess Qinghe?
เจ้าเป็นคนของท่านหญิงหนิงเหอ
The names listed in the letter
รายชื่อทั้งหมดบนจดหมาย
are loyal followers of General Shi.
ล้วนเป็นคนสนิทของท่านแม่ทัพสื่อ
Most of them
ซึ่งส่วนใหญ่
aren't willing to support Chen Yintai.
ล้วนไม่ยินดีสนับสนุนเฉินอิ้นไถ
The relay stations
ออกจากค่ายไปทางตะวันตกสิบลี้
10 li west from the camp
เรือนรับรองซื่อฟาง
are waiting for your orders, my lady.
ยินดีรับคำสั่งจากแม่นาง
My ladies,
ผู้แทนพระองค์ทั้งสอง
our general is requesting for your presence.
ใต้เท้าของพวกเราให้เชิญขอรับ
Two of you, follow me.
พวกเจ้าสองคนรีบไปกับเรา
Who are you?
เจ้าเป็นใคร
I'm Zuo Qianwei,
ข้าเป็นองครักษ์ลับของ
the secret bodyguard of Official Huang.
ใต้เท้าหวงแห่งกองพันซ้ายเชียนหนิวเว่ย
I've been assigned to stay here and relay information.
รับผิดชอบเรื่องส่งข่าวจากที่นี่
My lady, I'm here to protect you under his order.
รับคำสั่งให้มาคอยรับแม่นาง
- Thank you.
- ขอบคุณ
What should we do next?
หลังจากนี้พวกเราควรทำอย่างไร
Should we head to the relay stations?
ไปเรือนรับรองซื่อฟาง
Ziyuan,
จื่อย่วน
bring him
เจ้าพาองครักษ์ลับท่านนี้
to the relay stations
ไปเรือนรับรอง
and meet up with Princess Ninghe's men.
สมทบกับคนของท่านหญิงหนิงเหอ
Tell them not to act.
บอกพวกเขาว่าอย่าเพิ่งเคลื่อนไหว
His Majesty has a way to deal with this.
ฝ่าบาททรงมีวิธีจัดการ
What about you?
แล้วเจ้าล่ะ
Someone assaulted the camp.
เหตุวุ่นวายในค่ายทหารคืนนี้
I must get to the bottom of this.
ข้าต้องไปตรวจสอบให้กระจ่าง
I'll meet up with you later.
เดี๋ยวจะตามไปสมทบกับเจ้า
Take care.
ถนอมตัวด้วย
Is General Chen dead?
แม่ทัพเฉินตายง่าย ๆ แบบนี้เหรอ
I saw his body for myself.
ข้าเห็นด้วยตาของตัวเอง
Official Zhang Jiang was the one who killed him.
ใต้เท้าจางเจียงลงมือ
With one swing,
ฟันฉับ
his head rolled to the floor.
หัวตกลงพื้น
General Chen's reign
แม่ทัพเฉินยังนั่งเก้าอี้
was short-lived.
ไม่ทันจะร้อนเลย
My men from Lucong had reported back to me.
หลูฉงแจ้งว่า
Three days ago,
สามวันก่อน
Chen Yintai
เฉินอิ้นไถได้ต้อนรับ
had met up with His Majesty's envoy.
ผู้แทนพระองค์ของฝ่าบาท
And I
ส่วนข้า
knew nothing about it.
กลับไม่รู้อะไรสักอย่าง
But Grandfather,
ท่านปู่
Qi Yan didn't send anyone to meet him.
แต่ฉีเยี่ยนไม่ได้ส่งใครไปนะ
Who said so?
ใครบอกว่าไม่
He sent Cheng Ruoyu!
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
It's my fault.
เป็นลูกไม่ดี
I fell
เป็นลูกไม่ดีที่หลงกล
for her trick.
แผนล่อเสือออกจากถ้ำของนาง
You.
เจ้า
You told me
บอกข้ามาเดี๋ยวนี้
that she went to Zhaoyi.
เขาไปจ้าวอี๋
And you,
ส่วนเจ้า
you said Liu Congjian stationed his troops at Zhaoyi
เจ้าบอกว่าหลิวฉงเจียนสะสมทหารที่จ้าวอี๋
and he was up to no good.
เจตนาไม่บริสุทธิ์
And you!
เจ้าด้วย
You said there was nothing to report about
เจ้าบอกว่าสายสืบตามทาง
during your surveillance.
ไม่มีรายงานใด ๆ
I only received news regarding
ส่วนข่าวจากหลูฉง
the incident in Lucong after three days!
ก็มาล่าช้าไปถึงสามวัน
Ever since Han Yue murdered the Two Chariots,
นับตั้งแต่คู่เชอถูกหานเยว่ฆ่าตาย
Lucong
หลูฉงก็พลอยเละเทะ
turned into a mess.
ตามไปด้วย
It's time for us to rectify our mistake.
สมควรจัดระเบียบได้แล้ว
It was my negligence.
ลูกทำงานบกพร่อง
I wasn't able to atone for my mistake in time.
ไม่อาจอุดรอยรั่วได้ทันกาล
Right Minister,
โย่วซื่อ ถ่ายทอดคำสั่ง
keep an eye on them in secret.
สายสืบตามทาง
Wang Lin!
หวังหลิน
Yes, my lord.
บริวารอยู่นี่
Send troops to guard the city's gate.
เจ้าส่งทหารไปเฝ้าประตูเมือง
If you see Cheng Ruoyu,
เจอเฉิงรั่วอวี๋เมื่อไร
kill her immediately.
ให้ฆ่าทันที
Yes, Grandfather.
ขอรับ ท่านปู่
All of you, get up.
ลุกขึ้นให้หมด
Father,
ท่านพ่อ
these are the court officials who Li Deyun had visited
นี่คือรายชื่อขุนนาง
for the past period.
ที่หลี่เต๋ออวิ๋นไปพบในช่วงนี้
Have some water.
ดื่มน้ำก่อน
If you followed
หากเจ้าทำตามที่ฉิวเยียนจือบอก
Qiu Yanzhi's instruction
ลงมือฆ่าเฉินอิ้นไถ
and killed Chen Yintai from the start,
ทันทีที่เจอหน้า
we didn't need to go through all this trouble.
ก็คงไม่ต้องลำบากแบบนี้
How could I do so?
จะทำอย่างนั้นได้อย่างไร
Chen Yintai
เฉินอิ้นไถ
was murdered by Zhang Jiang, General of the Standard.
ถูกผู้บังคับกองพันจางเจียงฆ่า
That means the Lucong army wasn't satisfied with his command.
เป็นการบอกว่าทหารในหลูฉงไม่ยอมรับ
After his death,
เขามาตายแบบนี้
I guess the others he had colluded with
กลุ่มอิทธิพลต่าง ๆ ที่เขาติดต่อ
will stop acting for now.
ก็หยุดความเคลื่อนไหวลงชั่วคราว
We need to hurry back.
พวกเราต้องรีบกลับไป
We need to report this to them.
รายงานเรื่องนี้โดยด่วน
I almost forgot.
ใช่สิ
You're in a hurry to return
เจ้าต้องรีบกลับไป
in order to claim credits from your darned emperor.
รายงานความชอบกับฮ่องเต้สุนัขของเจ้า
Do you really think
เจ้าคิดจริง ๆ หรือว่า
that the situation will be better
หากอ๋องกวงได้ขึ้นครองราชย์แล้ว
if Prince Guang ascended the throne?
ทุกอย่างจะดีกว่าในเวลานี้
At least Prince Guang is a good guy.
อย่างน้อยอ๋องกวงก็เป็นคนดี
His Majesty isn't a villain.
ฝ่าบาทก็ไม่ใช่คนเลว
The darned emperor acknowledged a eunuch as his father.
ฮ่องเต้สุนัขเรียกขันทีเป็นพ่อ
He had to bow down to him and lick his boots.
คุกเข่าก้มหัวไร้สง่าบารมี
Prince Guang hasn't
อ๋องกวงไม่เคยเลีย
licked Qiu Ziliang's boots at all.
รองเท้าของฉิวจื่อเหลียง
But, he's living in seclusion.
แต่เขาเก็บตัวเร้นกาย
He's escaping from the mess.
หลบหนี
Not only did His Majesty not escape from this mess,
ฝ่าบาทมิเพียงไม่หนี
he's bearing every sin
กลับแบกรับความผิด
and humiliation by himself.
เสียงก่นด่าประณามทั้งหมดเอาไว้
After his ascension,
หลังจากพระองค์ขึ้นครองราชย์
he was determined
ก็ทรงงานอย่างหนัก
to get rid of the eunuch's faction.
คิดขจัดอำนาจขุนนาง
That's why Qiu Ziliang
ดังนั้นฉิวจื่อเหลียง
tried to assassinate him
จึงได้พยายามจะสังหารพระองค์
time and time again.
ครั้งแล้วครั้งเล่า
If you were right about the situation,
หากเป็นอย่างที่เจ้าคิดละก็
why didn't he follow his every command?
ทำไมพระองค์ไม่ก้มหัวคุกเข่าไปให้ตลอดล่ะ
Damn it.
บัดซบ
We would've arrived
หากไม่เพื่อหลบเลี่ยง
three days earlier
สายสืบของสำนักหมากรุก
if we didn't need to avoid the spy from the Generals of Chess Camp.
คงมาถึงตั้งแต่เมื่อสามวันก่อนแล้ว
Today will be the end of our two-month deadline.
วันนี้ครบกำหนดสองเดือนแล้ว
Will we be able to make it?
ทันหรือเปล่า
The gate has a tight security.
ประตูเมืองตรวจตราเข้มงวด
Entering the city will be an arduous task.
เกรงว่ายากจะเข้าไป
What should we do then?
แล้วทำอย่างไรดี
The morning court has started.
การประชุมเช้าเริ่มแล้ว
Let's go.
ไป
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
the two-month deadline is up.
กำหนดสองเดือนได้ครบแล้ว
Official Li Deyun,
ใต้เท้าหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋น
so, what should we do
เรื่องที่หลูฉง
about the incident in Lucong?
ควรจัดการเช่นไร
During the rebellion of Heshuo,
จากกรณีเหอซั่วเมื่อในอดีต
in order to settle the dispute,
ราชสำนักเพื่อปลอบขวัญประชา
we sent envoys to deliver the imperial edict.
จึงใช้การส่งทูตไปประกาศราชโองการ
But, by doing so,
แต่ในครั้งนี้
we'll be implicated instead.
กลับถูกยับยั้งมาโดยตลอด
The current situation in Lucong
บัดนี้สถานการณ์ในหลูฉง
is still undetermined.
ยังไม่ทราบผลแน่ชัด
Even if Chen Yintai is requesting for a post,
ต่อให้เฉินอิ้นไถต้องการขวานอาญาสิทธิ์
we should
มิสู้
ignore him
ทำไม่สนใจ
and observe as the situation unfolds.
รอดูสถานการณ์
Official Li Deyun,
หลี่เต๋ออวิ๋น ใต้เท้าหลี่
you were given two months
ท่านใช้เวลาถึงสองเดือนเต็ม ๆ
to settle this dispute.
เพื่อวางแผน
In the end, you're telling us to ignore the matter
สุดท้ายมาพูดว่าทำไม่สนใจ
and observe as the situation unfolds?
รอดูสถานการณ์
Is that all from you?
ก็จบเรื่องหรือ
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
Official Li swore he would receive military punishment if he failed.
ใต้เท้าหลี่เคยถวายหนังสือทัณฑ์บน
He said he would settle the dispute in Lucong
บอกว่าภายในสองเดือน
within two months.
จะคลี่คลายเหตุการณ์ในหลูฉงให้ได้
But now,
วันนี้
time is up.
ครบกำหนดแล้ว
Your Majesty, please pursue responsibility.
ขอฝ่าบาททรงมีพระอาญา
Official Li's plan is a long-term plan.
แผนของใต้เท้าหลี่เป็นแผนระยะยาว
Although the situation in Lucong is still undetermined,
แม้เหตุการณ์ที่หลูฉงจะยังไม่มีบทสรุป
I assume Chen Yintai
แต่เฉินอิ้นไถ
has no countermeasures to it.
ก็ยังคงไร้ทางรับมือเช่นกัน
Lucong is quite far away.
หลูฉงหนทางไกล
I'm sure we'll receive news
คาดว่ารออีกสักหลายวัน
after a few more days.
น่าจะมีข่าวมา
No.
ไม่ได้
He was given two months.
ตกลงว่าสองเดือน
Now, the deadline is up.
ก็ต้องสองเดือน
We need to pursue responsibility immediately.
ลงอาญาในตอนนี้
So what if we receive news
หากวันหน้ามีตัวแปรอะไรมา
after a few days?
แล้วจะรับมือเช่นไร
Isn't it disgraceful for him
บ่ายเบี่ยงเช่นนี้
not to keep his promise?
ไม่น่าสังเวชหรือไร
This is?
นี่คือ
This is the secret path to the Chess of Generals Camp.
ทางลับที่ทะลุถึงสำนักหมากรุก
Are you out of your mind?
จะบ้าหรือ
Don't tell me you want to let them arrest you?
เจ้าคิดรนหาที่ตายหรืออย่างไร
We'll only be able to avoid
มีเพียงทางลับสายนี้เท่านี้
being spied on by Qiu Ziliang's men if we use this path.
ที่ไม่ถูกคนของฉิวจื่อเหลียงจับตา
Let's hurry.
รีบไป
Fine, we can use this path.
เข้าไปน่ะได้
But, have you thought of a way
แต่เจ้าคิดหรือยังว่าจะออกจาก
to escape from the Chess of Generals Camp?
สำนักหมากรุกอย่างไร
Qiu Yanzhi.
ฉิวเยียนจือ
We can ask Qiu Yanzhi to help us.
ให้ฉิวเยียนจือช่วยเรา
You do trust her.
เจ้าช่างไว้ใจนางเหลือเกิน
We're out of time.
ตอนนี้พวกเราไม่มีเวลามากพอ
I don't have time to worry about this.
ให้สนใจอะไรมากความแล้ว
We need to make this bet.
วัดดวงดู
Let's go.
ไป
(Yu'er,)
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
(even now, you haven't returned.)
วันนี้เจ้ายังไม่กลับ
(Did something happen to you?)
หรือเกิดอะไรกับเจ้า
Come.
มา
Let's go.
ไป
Who are you?
พวกเจ้าเป็นใคร
I'll stall them. Just go.
ข้าจะถ่วงพวกมันไว้ เจ้ารีบไป
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
a promise is a promise.
กษัตร์ตรัสแล้วไม่คืนคำ
Your Majesty, please issue an imperial edict
ขอทรงมีพระราชโองการ
and strip Li Deyun of his post.
ปลดหลี่เต๋ออวิ๋น
All of you may rise.
ทุกคนลุกขึ้น
Thank you, Your Majesty.
ขอบพระทัยฝ่าบาท
The chaos within the prefectures
เหตุวุ่นวายที่หัวเมือง
is still ongoing.
ยังไม่ทันสงบ
Although it's the fault of my subject,
แม้เป็นความผิดเขา
it's my responsibility as well.
ข้าก็ต้องรับผิดชอบ
I'm willing to issue an imperial edict to take the blame
ข้าจะมีราชโองการตำหนิตัวเอง
on behalf of Official Li.
เพื่อรับผิดในครั้งนี้แทนใต้เท้าหลี่
No.
ไม่ได้
Your Majesty, if you do this,
หากทำเป็นตัวอย่าง
in the future, you'll be able
เอะอะฝ่าบาท
to take the blame for your incompetent subjects.
ก็ทรงรับผิดแทนขุนนางไร้สามารถ
The law would be useless by then.
แล้วกฎหมายอยู่ที่ใดเล่า
The law?
กฎหมาย
I'm the one who makes the law.
ข้าเป็นคนกำหนด
I am
ข้า
the law.
ก็คือกฎหมาย
♪Life is a dream, how long do happy times last♪
♪ชีวิตล่องลอยดุจฝัน เคยสุขกี่ครั้ง♪
♪The sword can't break this karma♪
♪ชักดาบฟันฟาด กลับมิอาจสะบั้นเหตุและผล♪
♪Look how blurry and lonely the world is♪
♪มองฟ้ามองดินล้วนไม่ยินไม่แยแส♪
♪Still can't let go of this life as time goes by♪
♪ตะวันรุ่งจันทราโรย ชีพนี้ยังคงน่าถนอม♪
♪Even the iron and golden dagger-axe cannot extinguish the fire in my heart♪
♪ควบอาชาพร้อมอาวุธ มิอาจหยุดไฟในทรวง♪
♪Remembering the past and letting time while away♪
♪คิดถึงฝันในวันเก่า นานเท่านาน ยังคงเจ็บ♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪